like this video and subscribe for these
hero animals
this brave guard dog springs into action
to save this boy from a stranger
[Music]
even though this toddler wasn't in
immediate danger this cat was not taking
any chances with it
a leopard charges this zookeeper from
behind but his tiger friend is there to
save the day
in training this dog shows that it will
do anything to protect its family
this whale protected this woman from
what would be a lethal tiger shark
attack
he came right for me he didn't stop
they kept pushing
instead of a guard dog here we have a
guard horse
[Music]
this kid pretended to have difficulty
swimming but his dog did not get the
joke
[Music]
rather than attacking this gorilla comes
over to an injured boy to see if he can
comfort him
this
[Music]
a man was whisked away in the river but
this elephant wasted no time in spring
into action
this very angry goose tried to attack
this dog's owner
[Music]
this dog refuses to go to sleep until
everybody in the house is tucked into
bed
cat comes to the rescue when it matters
the most
[Music]
this man has two overprotective dogs
that aren't too happy with him swinging
into the river
kitty saves toddler from tumbling down a
massive flight of stairs
[Music]
a stranger walks into this woman's home
but her great dane is there to show him
he made a mistake
[Music]
this german shepherd led firefighters to
a fire that they simply could not find
i find the fire which was threatening
the uh heinrich cole
recognized that something was unusual
when he saw buddy
this dog decides to quit stay job and
become a crossing guard
up
[Music]
dog's owner has a seizure and flags down
anyone for help
[Music]
billy says she is forever thankful
this horse teams up with experts to find
a missing two-year-old that was lost in
the woods
to the hearty creek trailhead i i just
kind of followed instinct and really
felt where would this person be and they
were crying
so i said to wilson go get her show some
of the way and he did wilson's red one
he's my uh these are
miniature strange shepherds
[Music]
oh
he's trying to save you
you say he's heavy
tight
in this last viewer submitted image as
you can see a dog saves a baby from the
bottom of a pool talk about the perfect
hero