Humans are filling up the space
around Earth with trash.
ARCHIVE: “three, two...”
Decades of space exploration that began
with a single satellite launch in 1957...
ARCHIVE: “One of the great scientific feats of the age.”
Have left discarded rocket bodies,
mission-related debris and thousands
of satellites – many of them long abandoned
and no longer functional –
crisscrossing at high speeds
just above Earth's atmosphere.
And with a booming space industry
launching more objects into orbit
than ever before, this crowding
is steadily increasing
the probability of catastrophic
in-orbit collisions.
Scientists worry that a runaway
chain reaction of collisions
and fragmentation could
one day fill Earth's orbit
with so much debris that space
will become unusable to humans.
It's why the world's leading space
agencies and some for-profit
companies are working on big ideas
to fix our space debris problem.
From trash collecting spacecraft
armed with harpoons and nets...
to a giant cloud of metal dust.
And there's one solution
that's been proposed for years
to halt these dangerous bits
of garbage in their tracks.
Lasers.
Because if we get creative
and start addressing this problem
right now, we can still fix it
before it's too late.
The vast majority of human-made objects
surrounding Earth are here – in a
region called “low Earth orbit.”
It's where we have communication
satellites, plus spacecraft
like the International Space Station.
And our massive amount of space trash.
The more objects we put in space
means more chances of these objects
smash into each other,
break apart, and multiply.
And all it takes is a handful
of fragmentation events to dramatically
increase the total number of objects
orbiting Earth. Like in 2009,
when a defunct Russian satellite
accidentally collided
with a commercial satellite, exploding
into thousands of trackable fragments.
And in 2007,
when China intentionally destroyed one
of its own satellites in a weapons test.
Which also resulted in tens of thousands
of fragments of varying sizes of debris.
A theoretical cascade effect
called the "Kessler syndrome,"
introduced in the 1970s, warned
that if enough incidents like these occur,
the fragments of debris
they create could trigger
an uncontrollable number
of catastrophic collisions.
Exponentially increasing
the field of debris around Earth.
But we can still fix this
before it's too late.
And there's a few ways it could happen.
The way to get rid of most space
debris is to slow it down enough to fall
out of orbit and into Earth's atmosphere,
where it burns up and is destroyed.
But different sized space junk requires
different approaches to do this.
The biggest bits of space debris measure
more than 10 centimeters in size
This includes dead
satellites, rocket bodies
and big pieces of debris
created during space missions.
These are large enough
to be tracked from Earth.
And scientists are developing
tiny spacecraft
that can reach these objects
and slow them down, using various
methods to either push or pull them.
Guiding them down to Earth's
atmosphere to be destroyed.
Commercial companies
like Europe's ClearSpace
and Japan's Astroscale are working with
global space agencies on this tech.
Hoping to demonstrate the removal of large
debris sometime in the next decade.
The two smaller classifications
of space debris mostly
come from fragmentation events
like explosions and collisions.
Their numbers are estimates because
we still don't have the technology
in place to reliably track debris
below ten centimeters in size.
The tiniest pieces include flecks of paint
and metal that even at a fraction
of a millimeter in size, regularly
cause minor damage to spacecraft.
So far, scientists have proposed
two main ideas to remove these.
One: a physical sweeper placed in orbit
that could catch or slow them down
enough to de-orbit them.
But this approach for removal,
at least as far as NASA's concerned,
is too expensive to even consider.
The other, more cost effective solution
would be to release a cloud
of tungsten dust on top of the debris.
Which would coat the objects
and weigh them down,
dragging them into Earth's atmosphere
to be destroyed. On the other hand,
dumping a 20 ton cloud
of heavy metal dust into Earth's
orbit could end up contributing
to the pollution of space.
So it hasn't been tried yet.
As of right now, the sweeper and tungsten
dust ideas probably aren't
practical solutions.
But there's another option for this class
of space debris in the middle.
It presents a unique problem.
Because at 1 to 10 centimeters,
this debris is too small to track,
but big enough to do serious damage.
Just one fragment, even one centimeter
in size, moving at an average speed
of seven kilometers per second is powerful
enough to knock out a satellite.
Analysis from NASA shows
that focusing on this range of debris
would be highly effective in managing
the space debris problem as a whole.
This is where the lasers come in.
Lasers can direct a beam of energy
and apply force to an object
without ever making physical contact.
They could be used to nudge a
fast-moving piece of small debris
and disrupt its orbit – either knocking it
into higher, less crowded levels of orbit,
or lowering it into Earth's
atmosphere to be destroyed
This method is sometimes
referred to as a "laser broom."
A ground-based laser system was proposed
by NASA's Project Orion in 1996.
And according to NASA's 2023 cost and benefit
analysis of space debris removal methods,
A ground- or space-based laser system
would be the most cost-effective way.
to remove this class of
1 to 10 centimeter size debris.
But historically, not everyone
has loved this idea.
CLAUDE PHIPPS: People were resistant
to the idea of lasers in space.
Because all the spy satellties were worried
they might get blinded.
But now they starting to come around.
Claude Phipps was a part of Project Orion back in the nineties,
and is who originally proposed
this idea in the US
to deal with space debris
using lasers.
PHIPPS: It’s a fairly simple idea.
A ground-based laser for debris
removal would basically work like this:
First, a radar system
would detect a small piece
of debris coming over the horizon
and lock onto its position.
Because while these objects
are too small to track when out of sight,
they can be sufficiently tracked as they
shoot across the sky long enough to aim
the telescope that focuses the laser
and fire a near-instantaneous
pulse of energy through the atmosphere
with remarkable precision.
A space based laser would work similarly,
with a couple key differences.
One advantage of being in orbit
is that these lasers
would have a more favorable angle to shoot
debris downward into Earth's atmosphere.
And they wouldn't need to correct
for Earth's atmosphere or long distances
when aiming – like a ground-based system would.
Making a space-based solution
potentially more efficient.
But, being in space,
it wouldn't have access to Earth's
power grid, and would be
much more difficult to maintain.
PHIPPS: The laser on the ground is going to be cheaper.
But the geometry is kind of screwed up.
If you’re on the ground, you're having to shoot it this way
Whereas in space, you can see everywhere you know.
And hundreds of thousands of these things are available
when you’re in orbit.
Shoot this one, shoot that one,
shoot the other one. As often as you want.
That same NASA cost and benefit report
suggested that a laser system
could be highly effective for dealing
with large debris too. By nudging the debris
out of the way of a spacecraft's orbit
when an incoming collision is detected,
This method would be more cost effective
than sending spacecraft to
retrieve the debris, and potentially
safer than dragging it back
in Earth's atmosphere.
Since especially large pieces of debris
aren't guaranteed
to be destroyed, and could pose a threat
to people on the ground.
Claude told me that we have the technology
now to develop ground- and space-based
lasers to fight space debris.
But there's one big thing
that's standing in the way.
PHIPPS: It all comes down to money. It's
not a question of knowing what to do –
it's a question of people committing to it.
There are a couple commercial companies
around the world working on it.
And we may not be so far away from
a future where ground- and space-based
laser systems are sweeping
the night sky of space debris.
There's one more problem we need to confront
before we start cleaning up space, though.
Right now, international space
law forbids any body from touching
an object in space that it didn't launch.
So even if a Japanese company
like EX-Fusion or NASA do develop
a laser broom, they couldn't use it
on a dead Russian satellite, for example.
PHIPPS: The lawyers have to work that out.
And where there's a will, there's a way.
That's the way I look at it.
Cleaning up this mess is going to require
an international effort and cooperation
from commercial actors like SpaceX.
But removing what's up there isn't
the only way to deal with the problem.
The European Space Agency's Zero Debris
Charter, announced in June 2023, emphasizes
mitigation of space debris – preventing
the creation of new debris going forward.
By committing to things
like designing satellites
that reenter Earth's atmosphere
on their own
after completing their missions –
instead of sitting in space as trash.
In the US, the FCC introduced a new five year
rule in September 2022 that said
US-based spacecraft put into low Earth
orbit must de-orbit themselves
within five years of mission's end.
Efforts like these are just the beginning.
But a combination of remediation
and mitigation efforts is projected
to make serious progress in
battling our space debris problem.
If everyone using space as a resource
can change their habit
of littering before it's too late.
Before you go, we have something
we’re excited to share with you.
It’s a special video coming out in March
for members of our Vox Contributions program.
The Vox Contributions program helps fund our journalism through direct support from viewers like you.
As a thank you to our recurring contributors, our video team has put together an exclusive video tutorial
in which our art director, Joey,
will walk you through the process of making the
classic Vox document highlight animation.
Head over to vox.com/givenow  to join us and keep an
eye out for that video in the coming weeks.
Thanks for watching